<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to Mr. Fitz-Gerald's state of the case concerning the patent of making salt water fresh</title>
            <author>Walcot, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W285A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13099551</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13099551</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 402:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to Mr. Fitz-Gerald's state of the case concerning the patent of making salt water fresh</title>
                  <author>Walcot, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Walcot. Cf. BM; Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Licens'd, Jan. 16, 1694/5. D. Poplar"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fitzgerald, R. --  (Robert). --  Salt-water sweetned.</term>
               <term>Seawater --  Distillation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97399:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. FITZ-GERALD's State of the CASE Concerning the PATENT OF <hi>Making Salt Water Freſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Licens'd,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Jan.</hi> 16. 1694/5.</date>
                        <signed>D. Poplar.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:97399:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97399:2"/>
            <head>A Preliminary to the Work.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MR.</hi> Fitz-Gerald<hi>'s Publiſhing his State of the Caſe, ſheweth the Neceſſity that it ſhould be Anſwered, and ſufficiently Juſtifieth the Deſign of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, which needs not any Recommendation. When there is an Art found out by ſome perſon, which might be Infinitely Advantageous to the Publick, and is known to be Demonſtratively True in it ſelf; and (though the Secrets thereof are yet undiſcovered) many are ariſen up Pretenders to it, who ſharply Contend to Enjoy to Themſelves the Exerciſe of it, whether they underſtand it or not, carrying the Noiſe through ſeveral Nations, and Troubling the World about it, Few perſons are ſo extraordinarily Employed, but will probably ſpare ſome of their Minutes to be ſatisfied in the Truth of this matter; to be able to judge whoſe the Right is, and who do the Wrong, that the Right Perſon may be Encouraged chearfully to proceed, and the Wrong be reſtrained wholly from med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling. They may be known, both the one and the other, by their Proofs and paſt actions: It is too well underſtood that Mr.</hi> Fitz-Gerald, <hi>with his Partners, had long ago Obſtructed Mr.</hi> Walcot<hi>'s Letters Patents granted for his Art of making Sea-water Freſh, Clear and Wholeſome, by procuring a Patent for themſelves, and had taken great Freedom of the Preſs to Prejudice</hi> W. W. <hi>And the two laſt Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Parliament ſet themſelves to oppoſe the Paſſing of his Bill, and brought in their ſtate of the Caſe (as they termed it) to the Committee of the Lords,</hi> March 1692, <hi>(which is placed Entire on the next following ſide.) This forceth a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of giving an account of the Truth, and to unravel the whole matter, which they would on purpoſe make perplexed, and unintelligible. They ever ſince their firſt appearing to Contend, have inceſſantly buſied themſelves in Solliciting Great Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages to maintain their Intereſt againſt</hi> W. W. <hi>And if by their Specious Pretences they have ſo far Prevailed with any as to give them Countenance,</hi> W. W. <hi>is apt to believe, that thoſe Honourable Perſons they have preſumed to Apply to, when rightly informed of the very Truth of the Caſe between Him and Them, and their Manner of Dealing, will ſoon withdraw their Favour, and leave them to themſelves. But if Mr.</hi> Fitz-Gerald <hi>with his Partners can ſtill ſucceed in Freventing</hi> W. W. <hi>to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an Act of Parliament, the Benefit of the Art will be Loſt to the Nation, which is obvious in the ſubſequent Narrative. It is not intended to anticipate the Minds of any Perſons, but to open the Matter gradually, only as Mr.</hi> Fitz Gerald <hi>offers the Occaſion, that thereby a true Judgment may be made, by any Perſon, on the Whole.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97399:3"/>
            <head>The State of the <hi>CASE</hi> concerning the Patent of making <hi>Salt Water Freſh,</hi> as it stands between Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> of the one part, and the Lord <hi>Falkland, William Bridgman</hi> Eſq Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> and ſeveral others on the other part.</head>
            <p>KIng <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, about ſixteen years ſince, Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> a Patent for making <hi>Salt Water Freſh,</hi> with a particular Clauſe, That he ſhould put the ſame in Execution within ſeven years, or ſome leſs time, or his Patent ſhould be void; and with this farther Condition, That if at any time hereafter it ſhould appear to be inconvenient or prejudicial to His Majeſty's Subjects, and made ſo to appear to ſix of the Privy Councel, it ſhould for that reaſon be void, and his Patent ſoon after to be Cancelled; His Majeſty ſoon after this Grant, was invited by Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> to ſee the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Engine and Invention, which was of too great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſion, and ſo extreamly hot, and for other Cauſes then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, it was not found Practicable at Sea, and about ſix years after the ſaid Grant to Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> upon the Encouragement of the late Mr. <hi>Boyl,</hi> made a Diſcovery of a new, eaſie and practicable way of making <hi>Salt Water Freſh</hi> and Wholſome at <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi> having obtained great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit among Sea men, Phyſicians and others; the King Granted a Patent to Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> and others; to oppoſe which, Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> entered a Caveat, and after full hearing by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, learned on both ſides, the Patent of <hi>Walcot</hi> was laid aſide, and a Patent granted to Us the ſaid Patentees, which hath been ſince put in practice both by Sea and Land, to the ſatisfaction of all Perſons who have not been influenced by their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intereſts.</p>
            <p>There being a Bill brought in by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> to deſtroy the Right of our Patent, in which there are about five years unexpired.</p>
            <p>It is therefore Humbly Prayed the ſaid Bill may not paſs, to the prejudice of the ſaid Letters Patents of Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> and his Partners, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> having conſented to an Agreement under them, as will be ready to be produced.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> can obtain an Act of Parliament in prejudice of this Patent, which ſeems unreaſonable, it is hoped it will be with a ſaving to Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>'s Patent, that of Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi>'s being expired as to time, and vacated by his own Conſent, as will appear on the Hearing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97399:3"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>'s State of the Caſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Patent of Making Salt Water Freſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein appears Whoſe the Right is to Exerciſe the Art.</head>
            <p>WHen the Committee of the Lords, appointed by the Right Honourable the Houſe of Lords, had taken into their Conſideration, a Bill which had Paſſed the Houſe of Commons, and was Carried to the Lords for their Concurrence; intituled, <hi>An Act, for making Sea-water Freſh, Clear, and Whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> and their Lordſhips in the Committee had alſo Paſſed it, and was by Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> and his Partners Petition Recommitted, as will be ſhewn more at large; Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> gave in a Paper Printed, Entituled, <hi>The State of the Caſe concerning the Patent, &amp;c.</hi> which was the Subſtance of what his Councel vehemently urged; wherein the True Caſe between Them, and Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> was wholly Miſrepreſented; wherefore now the Buſineſs is to inquire into it, by every Part thereof ſeverally as it falls in, as well the Title, (which ought not to be paſſed by without ſome Cenſure) as <hi>His State of the Caſe;</hi> and what the Truth is, ſhall be laid open. Both the Title and Caſe are all along Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the Anſwer by a Line Intervening, and ſo may be Read apart from the Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1. The State of the Caſe concerning the Patent of making Salt water freſh.</note> The Firſt Patent being Granted to <hi>William Walcot</hi> Eſq in the Year 1675. <hi>Robert Fitz-Gerald</hi> Eſq and his Partners precured an Order of Councel, <hi>October</hi> the 30th. 1683. that it ſhould be Conditionally made Void, On a Condition they never Performed.</p>
            <p>And in Proſecution of that Order, it was by Six of the Privy Councel made Void accordingly.</p>
            <p>Another Patent was Granted to <hi>Robert Fitz-Gerald,</hi> Eſq and his Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>June</hi> in the Year 1683. which, (though <hi>Wm. Walcot</hi> his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was in Being, he calls <hi>The Patent,</hi>) is ſuppoſed to be void in Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2. As it ſtands between Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> of the one part, and the Lord <hi>Falkland, Will. Bridgman,</hi> Eſq Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> and ſeveral others, on the other part.</note> Here Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> is pleaſed to Leave out the Names of ſome that were the Patentees, and to bring in an Honourable Perſon to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and make great his Title of the Caſe, who was not one in their Patent; ſo that the Caſe concerning the Patent ſtands not between Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> for the Firſt Patent was Granted to Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> ſolely, and the other to Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> and other Pretenders, that call themſelves the Patentees, who were five, <hi>viz. Robert Fitz-Gerald, Theophilus Oglethorp, William Bridgman, Patrick Traunt,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Maule,</hi> Eſquires. And Articles of agreement were propoſed to <hi>W. W.</hi> in the Names of theſe five only, and no other. Theſe five. Perſons drew in others of great Power and Intereſt, (perhaps to give great Summs of Money) to be of their Party, or to be admitted to Shares under them; whom Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> would ingage to Employ their whole Intereſts againſt Mr. <hi>Walcot:</hi> Who have no Reaſon, if they are come in under a bad Title, and have made but ill Bargains with his Adverſaries, whoſe Skill hath failed them, and their Money is loſt) to oppoſe his Right. Neither can they have any juſt Hopes or Poſſibility ever to Reſtore: themſelves that way; Wherefore ſome Perſons concerned who are Partners in the Profits of Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>'s Skill, have ſince acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they have been extreamly diſappointed in their Expectation, and have ſhewn that they have given off their hopes of Succeſs therein; and have withdrawn themſelves from that Intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97399:4"/>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3. King <hi>Charles</hi> II. about 16 years ſince, granted to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> a Patent for making Salt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter freſh.</note> Here begins Mr. <hi>Fitz-Geralds</hi> and the Patentees State of the Caſe, as he Repreſents it. It appears, he was very Careleſs in giving in the Compute of the Time of the Grant to Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> ſeeing he undertook to do it in the Firſt Place, which is much miſtaken in his Calculation: It being really in <hi>October</hi> 1675. Yet herein he doth acknowledge that <hi>W. W.</hi> had his Patent granted many Years before they had ever pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Invention.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4. With a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Clauſe that he ſhould put the ſame in execution within 7 years, or ſome leſs time, or his Patent ſhould be void.</note> And it is Remarkable, that he ſhould now in the next place, be ſo Particular in puting down the exact time Limited, when it appears by the very Patent, there is no ſuch Clauſe, ſo that it is only their Pleaſure to aſſert it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">5. And with this further condition, That if at any time hereafter, it ſhould appear to be <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient</hi> or <hi>prejudicial</hi> to his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and made ſo to appear to ſix of the Privy Council, it ſhould for that reaſon be void, and his Patent ſoon after to be Cancelled.</note> Here they ſpeak of a General Proviſo, which <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Councel told the Committee, is in all Patents, and is not to be doubted but is in theirs as well as in this; and if their Patent had been of force, would have been the bane of it, and undoubtedly have deſtroyed it, whenever it ſhould have been brought to the Teſt, either before the Council or otherwhere: The words of the Proviſo, they ſpeak of, are: <hi>Provided always, and theſe our Letters Patents, are and ſhall be upon this Condition; that if at any time during the ſaid Term—It ſhall be made appear to us, our Heirs or Succeſſors, or any ſix or more of Our or Their Privy Councel, That this our Grant is contrary to Law, or prejudicial or inconvenient to our Subjects in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; or that the ſaid Invention is not a new Invention as to the Publick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Exerciſe thereof within our Dominions, where the ſame ſhall be uſed, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or exerciſed then,</hi> &amp;c — But it was not made appear to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and his Council at the hearing before them, that <hi>W. W.</hi> his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention was not new (which Mr. <hi>Fitz. G.</hi> and his Partners by their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel labour'd to prove, tho it was againſt themſelves) neither could they make it appear, that this his Majeſtys Grant to <hi>W. W.</hi> was <hi>any way contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Law, or prejudicial, or inconvenicent to his Majeſtys Subjects in general,</hi> or to any of them; but only was apprehended inconvenient to Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners, they having wrongfully obtain'd a Patent, which by reaſon of this former Grant to <hi>W. W.</hi> could not take place. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at the hearing in Council, vindicated <hi>W. W.</hi> his Art, from all the aſperſions they would have caſt upon it, owned and juſtified thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Clauſes in his Patent that were not in theirs, thoſe being then read in his preſence: And declared that he highly approved of <hi>W. W.</hi> his Water, which he had ſeen him prepare and perfect; and that on his own knowledge <hi>W. W.</hi> had attained to the true Art, but gave no ſuch teſtimony what his Opponents could do.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">6. His Majeſty ſoon after this Grant was invited by Mr. <hi>Walcot,</hi> to ſee the Operation of his Engine and Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>W. W.</hi> would not preſume to invite his Majeſty; but his Majeſty meerly upon his own inclination came and ſaw <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Experiment.</p>
            <p>Here is by Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> a particular care taken to give People to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that it was after the Grant to <hi>W. W.</hi> of his Majeſties Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents that his Majeſty came to ſee his Operation, to the intent that what Objections his Majeſty made when he came, might ſtick and expoſe his Art to contempt; whereas it is manifeſt, that his Majeſties ſeeing the Operation, was not after, but before the Grant of his Letters Patents to him; which appears by the Judgment that his Majeſty in his Grant gave of it, in declaring <hi>Some Evident Demonstrations whereof, we have ſeen to our great ſatisfaction, and do believe, &amp;c.</hi> which could not have been ſaid or inſetted if he had not firſt ſeen it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <note place="margin">7. Which was of too great Dimenſion, and ſo extreamly hot, and for other Cauſes then appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it was not found practicable at Sea—</note> It having been already made manifeſt, that his Majeſties ſeeing <hi>W. W</hi>'s. Operation was before, not after (as is ſo confidently affirmed) his Patent was granted. It cannot but be neceſſarily concluded from thence, that his Majeſty was fully convinced and ſatisfied, in whatever Objections his Majeſty could make, before he would grant his Letters Patents, and commanded to be inſerted ſuch extraordinary Clauſes as before mentioned. But yet however, a further account ſhall be given; His Majeſty had good reaſon to enquire, and might well ſay as much as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97399:4"/>all this, and yet it might be no way to <hi>W. W.</hi>'s diſadvantage: For His Majeſty at his firſt taſting of <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Water, which was above a year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to ſee the Experiment, liked it ſo well, that it was his pleaſure to ſay, he could without further proof declare it to be undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly good; and ordered him to improve his Experiment by further tryals, till he ſhould bring it to a practical uſe and a perfect Art, (and to inform him from time to time how he proceeded.) When his Majeſty had Received an Account that this was done, he ſignified his Pleaſure was to ſee the Experiment himſelf. At that time by reaſon of the haſte, that was neceſſary to have all things as ſoon as might be in a Readineſs to ſatisfy his Majeſty, <hi>W. W.</hi> beſpake to be made (having found that Copper would Injure the Water) a Small Light Iron Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, or Kettle, not much differing from ſuch as are made for ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſes: (he deſpairing to have any moulded at firſt, without his continual attendance, agreeable to any of his models) ſuch an one he gave order for, that might be hit on without any hazard, to ſerve only for this occaſion, that his Majeſty might not be diſappointed; but this Furnace proved to be caſt of larger dimenſions, and far more thick than was directed; beſides that it was unſound: And to have another moulded more ſuitable to the purpoſe, required a long delay. Wherefore <hi>W. W.</hi> was obliged on neceſſity to ſhew with this what could be done, which was placed within the Partition of a Cellar: whither his Majeſty came attended by the late Lord <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and by ſeveral now Living, and preſently made theſe very material Objections. One was, that the Fire would not be ſafe in that manner, but be too hot for a Ship to endure; beſides the cumberſomeneſs of the Furnace as it then ſtood, could not do well in a Ship. Whereupon <hi>W. W.</hi> Anſwered, that no proviſion was made there, for ſecurity from danger of Fire, it being in a Cellar, but in a Ship proviſion ſhould be made accordingly againſt Danger of Fire; that what was here done, was Intended only to ſatisfy his Majeſty in the goodneſs of the Water, and that great Quantities might be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in a ſhort time. He not having the Opportunity (ſince he Expected his Majeſty, and not knowing how ſoon His Majeſty might come) to get Things made ready to be uſed there, which might be proper for Sea Service; and that neither that Furnace, nor any of thoſe Materials there placed, were Intended for a Ship, but far more Compleat, more Commodious; and eſpecially fitted for the Purpoſe. And another Objection that his Majeſty made, was, that there was a Joint which could not bear the motion of a Ship at Sea; to which <hi>W. W.</hi> anſwered, thas he had contrived his Furnaces each of them to be moulded all of a piece, that where that Joint was ſhould be none. And that he would Endeavour to have ſuch made, as ſoon as he could have leiſure, and find fit Iron, and able Work-men to do them; which was after done, and His Majeſty had an account thereof.</p>
            <p>By the means of what His Majeſty there ſaw done, and his Enquiries and Objections being Anſwered, His Majeſty was ſo well ſatisfied in all reſpects, having ſome of the Water that he ſaw compleated, brought to <hi>White-hall</hi> to be kept, that there upon he granted his Letters Patents, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring therein, as before-mentioned.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty declared likewiſe, that when He could hear that <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Inſtruments were fixed in a Ship, he would come to ſee them, and then would give what Directions he ſhould think fit. So that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's asking Queſtions was not upon any Diſlike, but that He would be further informed in the matter, and ſhewed that his mind was intent upon it, that He was well pleaſed with what He had ſeen, and that his deſires were to advance the ſucceſs of ſo excellent an Art.</p>
            <p>Now this Argument that Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> puts ſuch a <hi>Streſs</hi> upon, might be retorted upon himſelf, if his Argument were worth any thing; That <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Engine and Invention at</hi> Hull <hi>(or formerly elſewhere at Land, whilſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97399:5"/>they were ſuffered) was of too great Dimenſion, and ſo extreamly hot, and for other cauſes then appearing, it was not found practicable at Sea:</hi> It ſeems he cannot imagine that he who can have greater Furnaces provided, can have leſs; whether <hi>W. W.</hi> can have greater Furnaces Caſt ſome may poſſibly doubt, but whether he can have leſs (beſides Mr. <hi>Fitz-G.</hi>) none; Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>W. W.</hi> could have other of a different ſhape from that, or whether he could have materials made up different from thoſe, none can doubt.</p>
            <p>Concerning the conveniency of the Inſtruments, and their manner of placing, ſee the account given by Mr. <hi>John Shiſh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavit">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Teſtimonial of Mr. <hi>John Shiſh,</hi> Chief Maſter-Builder of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Yard at <hi>Deptford,</hi> concerning the working of <hi>W. W.</hi> his Inſtruments in Ships.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHereas</hi> William Walcot <hi> Eſq hath often diſcourſed with me about his ſetting up of his Furnaces and Inſtruments in Ships for his Invention of making Good Freſh Water, and hath let me ſee his Furnaces, Inſtruments and Materials, and one Furnace in particular built upon Boards in a Room, which I ſee hath been much uſed with ſecurity from Danger of Fire: I do Certifie, that it doth appear to me, that he hath taken great Care, made many Induſtrious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, and good Proviſion, for ſafety and Conveniency of Working in Ships, and that he hath brought his Furnaces, Inſtruments, and other Materials (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating them to Ship-Service) and manner of Placing them to a great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. I do Certifie likewiſe that they may be ſet up in a Ship without Damage or Injury to the Ship, with Security from danger of Fire, and able to endure the Motion and Toſſing of a Ship at Sea. And that, in my Opinion, it will be of great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe to Navagation, as well to His Majeſties Ships, as to others.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>May the 13th. 1681.</date>
                        <signed>John Shiſh.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This agreeth with the Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Which, He being ſent for to Give his Perſonal Attendance, not only Owned, but alſo declared before the then Lords Commiſſioners of the Admiralty, that He would undertake to ſet them up in the ſame manner in any of His Majeſties Ships, if they pleaſed to aſſign him a Ship for that Purpoſe, ſo that thereby they were become Witneſſes to his Teſtimonial.</q>
            <p n="8">8. <note place="margin">8. And about Six Years after the ſaid Grant to Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot</hi> Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>
               </note> Hereby it appears, that Mr. <hi>Fitz. G.</hi> acknowledgeth himſelf and his Partners not to be the Firſt and True Inventor, it having been declared in the Grant that <hi>W. W.</hi> had given <hi>Evident Demonſtrations</hi> of his Art, which was ſix years before he pretended to go about it, as himſelf ſaith, tho it was longer.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <note place="margin">9. Upon the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> made a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very —</note> That while Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> gave great Diſcouragements and Diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to <hi>W. W.</hi> whom he knew had obtained Letters Patents, by his making Proofs before his Majeſty, and had his Bill once read in the Houſe of Lords, which remained there; who was the <hi>Firſt and True In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> had need of ſome great Perſons Patronage, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendatory Letters, to Introduce and Prefer him, ſince he came ſo over-late, and ſo far out of ſeaſon, as to go about to make a Diſcovery of what was certainly diſcovered by another perſon ſix years before, as himſelf confeſſeth; and <hi>Evident Demonſtrations</hi> thereof ſhewn, and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents granted thereupon declaring the ſame, and when a good ſtock of Inſtruments and all ſorts of materials were made ready for the work.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <note place="margin">10. Of a New, Eaſy, and Practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way, of making Salt Water Freſh—</note> How New their way is, ſee afterwards.</p>
            <p n="11">11. And ſo Eaſie and Cheap, that their Engines and other Inſtruments, before they had at any time been uſed, were Expoſed to Sale, and offered for Old Goods, through want of having a vend for them to Sea, tho once, when firſt there were Tryals made with them, and before their effect was well known, they were dear enough.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97399:5"/>
            <p>And if Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> means by practicable, that their way is ſometimes uſed, it may well be granted, for they have done no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than what many years paſt has been done in Ships, in times of neceſſity, but not at other times uſed; The water having never been found to be good and wholeſome: See the States of <hi>Hollands</hi> Patent.</p>
            <p>If he means by practicable, generally, conſtantly practiſed, there ſeems but little ſign of that, Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> himſelf ſpeaks modeſtly in this; he told the Committee of the Houſe of Commons, that <hi>he was thouſands of pounds out of Purſe;</hi> yet did he plead that <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Bill ought not to paſs for this reaſon, becauſe Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> never got any thing by his Art, when Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> himſelf is the perſon that hath chiefly made it his buſineſs to obſtruct him, and hath thus long prevailed. So that the very reaſon that he urgeth for ſtopping his Bill, is a ſtrong reaſon that it ſhould paſs with as much ſpeed as may be; it being high time he ſhould get ſomething now towards his former Charges, who hath been ſo long moſt injuriouſly obſtructed.</p>
            <p>He did perſwade ſome perſons to buy their Engines and Ingredients for Sea, and be at the Expence of Trying to uſe them, but thoſe were too few to clear their Reckonings; what they gained this way could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver countervail the charge they put themſelves to; and they had great ſumms from his Majeſty for their Engines and Work at Land, whatever their performance was: All which it ſeemeth could not make them gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the whole. But altho Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> might get nothing clear in the main, by the practice of his Skill or work of his Engines, yet the while perhaps he might have found it encouraging and advantageous enough, to admit others to buy ſhares of his profits, which might yield an ample Recompence for what his pains and trouble herein could deſerve.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <note place="margin">12. And whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome at Sea and Land.</note> Some that have drank of their Water, and ſeen it prepared their way, ſay, and made proof of it before the Committee, that their Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was rough, harſh, fiery, Corroding, and tormenting the Body when conſtantly drank of; that they could know it by the ſmell, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome time it will putriſy, be baſe, and offenſive: whereas they ſay they find <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Sea-water to be ſmooth, ſoft, cooling, healing, and ſo pure, that they have known it laſt many years, and never ſaw in it any ſigns of Decay. Several Bottles of <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Water, were ſet on the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the Committees, both of the Lords and of the Commons, which were taſted by their Members, and much approved of; but Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> would not produce any. There was brought before the ſame Committee, at the ſame time</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavit">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Lord <hi>Chandos</hi> his Teſtimonial concerning his long Experience of <hi>VV. VV.</hi> his Sea Water.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THeſe are to Certifie All whom it doth or may Concern, That before I was Honoured with the Character of Ambaſſador from His Late Majeſty of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Memory to the Grand Seignior of the</hi> Turks, <hi>I had the Satisfaction of ſeveral Taſtes of my VVorthy Friend</hi> William Walcot <hi> Eſq his Sea-water made Freſh, and Sweet, and to all Intents and Purpoſes equally made uſeful with the beſt Spring-water that e're I drank of in</hi> England <hi>for Land or Sea Service, as, upon above ſeven years Experience thereof at home and in Foreign Parts, I am verily perſwaded. For of the ſaid Water I took with me ſome Quantity to</hi> Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>and there upon Trial thereof in the Preſence of ſeveral Perſons of Credit, found it exceeding Sweet and Good, inſomuch that I had the Curioſity to try how long it would ſo preſerve it ſelf in that hot Climate: And in that Experiment alſo it ſo well anſwered my Expectation, that after near ſeven years keeping of it abroad I brought of it home again with me: And now at this very time have of it,</hi> (viz. <hi>The water I took out with me from the ſaid Mr.</hi> Walcot) <hi>Right, Sweet, and Good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>In VVitneſs whereof I here Subſcribe my Name</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>this 25th <hi>of</hi> May, 1688.</date> Chandos.</dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>This agreeth with the Original of his Lordſhips own Hand-writing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97399:6"/>
            <p n="13">13. <note place="margin">13. Having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit among Seamen, Phyſicians and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> If they mean by Credit, ſuch a Belief that drew in great ſumms of money for purchaſing Shares of their Profits of them, perhaps they may find ſome that can at their Coſt witneſs for them; but if they mean by their great Credit, ſuch a full Belief of the Sufficiency of their way, as generally for men to truſt their Lives and Fortunes to the uſe of it, they could not before the Committees by any means make that out, the extent of their Skill ſeems to be too well known. No doubt, by ſuch plauſible means as they uſed to recommend and magnifie their Skill, the Credit they gained by Aſſuming to themſelves the Honour of <hi>W. W.</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention had continued very great, if they had been ſo cautious never to have ſhewn the Proof of their own: But herein their Policy failed them, for hereby they bewrayed their Skill. To raiſe the Credit of it, ſome Phyſicians Names they produced in Print, but produced not their own Hands; neither could thoſe be brought before the Committee to teſtifie any thing for them, but many whoſe Names they produced have decryed it. Though a Teſtimonial under the Hands of many of the Phyſicians of the Colledge in the year 1683 had been given to <hi>W. W.</hi> he had other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſuch abundant Ocular Teſtimony, that he had no occaſion before the Committee to have it mentioned: wherein are theſe words, <hi>We Do Declare, that We are</hi> (upon Examination of it, <hi>viz.</hi> Sea-water prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>W. W.) fully and ſufficiently ſatisfied that the ſaid Water is made very Freſh, Clear and Wholeſome, and Agreeable to the Body of Man.</hi> Their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony may be ſeen at large, when required. But had as many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as they had ever Importuned, ſubſcribed to the Wholeſomeneſs of their Water, yet it cannot be denied but that its Corroſiveneſs is obvious and offenſive both to the Taſte and Smell, and pernicious to the Body when conſtantly drank of, it being in many reſpects defective; concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Deficiency of the way that Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> pretends to render Salt-water wholeſome, there is a Scheme drawn to be ſeen upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and another drawn of the Sufficiency of <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Art.</p>
            <p>And that what they can do may be further known, the Lords of the States General of the United <hi>Netherlands</hi> (upon a Petition preſented to them on the behalf of <hi>W. W.</hi> that He and his Opponents might be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to appear before them, to make publick proofs of their Arts, and the States to judge whoſe Art was the beſt) and the Members of the States of the ſeveral Provinces, ſaw Mr. <hi>William Fitz-Gerald</hi> deputed by <hi>Robert Fitz-Gerald</hi> Eſq and his Partners, and <hi>W. W.</hi> each of them apart, thrice make their Tryals before them; whoſe approbation ſeems ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſatisfy in this matter. The States General granted thereupon to <hi>W. W.</hi> Their Letters Patents; and each of the States of the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> and <hi>Frizeland</hi> granted him their Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents ſeverally; all of them were <hi>To him alone, with excluſion of all others,</hi> wherein may be ſeen their judgment hereof, eſpecially and more at large in the Patent of the States of <hi>Holland.</hi> See the Preamble of their Patent; Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> and his Partners are there taken notice of, and an ample account is there given, what they found their skill to be; Our Sea-men alſo to whom they appeal, and others ha ve had experience of their Tryals, and well know the Credit their work is of. As well theſe as the States of <hi>Holland</hi> do aver, that any that will but diſtil Salt water ſhall find the Salt water ſo prepared in every reſpect, to be at leaſt equal, if not exceeding theirs. So that whatever their Helps and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have been, by what they have ſhewn and done, it appears that all they have found out, or made a Diſcovery of, is, <hi>That Water may be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled,</hi> (and certainly thoſe that know this, may know but little of the true Art) ſo that what Ingredients they add upon the conſideration of Salt water, doth not at all improve, but rather make the Water the worſe.</p>
            <p>Yet nevertheleſs Dr. <hi>N. G.</hi> put out a Treatiſe, dedicated to King <hi>Charles,</hi> undertaking to prove the Truth and Sufficiency of their Art (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97399:6"/>which there have been made Obſervations) concluding, That <hi>what thoſe Patentees have done will juſtly be accounted a Miracle.</hi> Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s long Letter, and alſo his Nicety, as he is pleaſed to call it, wherein he begs the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, have been Re-publiſhed in recommendation of it. <hi>And there was ſent to the Lord Mayor, cloſed in a Silver Box, ſealed up (with great ſelemnity) the Recitpts of the ſeveral Cements uſed by the Patentees for making Sea-water freſh, as alſo the Receipt of their Metalline Compoſition and Ingredients, certified under the hands of the Honourable Mr</hi> Robert Boyle, <hi>to be kept ſo ſealed up by the preſent and ſucceeding Lord Mayors, leſt a Secret of ſo great importance to the Publick might come to be loſt, if lodged only in the knowledge of a few Perſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concerned. See Londons Gazette, January</hi> 23, 1684.— Or leſt whilſt themſelves are buſie, taken up in the practiſing of their Art, they ſhould forget their Secrets wherewith they do it. A volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Song or Panegerick in Verſe was publiſhed in their Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and Medals engraven and caſt in ſilver, Repreſenting and Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Art, in Celebration of the <hi>laſt new Inventor.</hi> And whilſt they would have held all the World in admiration of their new Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (which ſome ſay in <hi>Gallens</hi> time was not known) they demand, by Vertue they ſay of an order of Council, that <hi>W. W.</hi> (the firſt and true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor of making Sea water freſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſhould pay, according to one of their Articles which they propoſed, after the hearing before his Majeſty in Councel in this manner. <hi>Item, It is agreed between the ſaid Parties to theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents; that the ſaid</hi> W. W. <hi>his Executors or Administrators, ſhall pay and allow out of the firſt Profits ariſing by the ſaid Art, the ſixth part of the Sum of fifteen hundred Pounds Sterling, which the ſaid Patentees have engaged to pay unto Mr.</hi> Jacob Kuffler, <hi>for his Aſſiſtance given them in the Invention of their Art, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of the Engine proper for the ſame.</hi>—Whom King <hi>Charles</hi> took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf to mention (when he was ſeeing <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Experiment) ſaying that he was very ſure that Mr. <hi>Kuffler</hi> had not the Art, which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſaid, when thoſe Perſons that attended him thither were in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, who can witneſs it. In the Dedication of the Book to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, owned by Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> it is ſaid — <hi>If the Fruits of your Royal Grant has not been hitherto derived to us, 'tis partly by ſome Obſtacles we met from the Suggeſtions of a private Perſon.</hi> And at the Council they pleaded that <hi>W. W.</hi> had no Art. And their Articles propoſed after the Orders of Council began thus—<hi>Whereas the ſaid</hi> W. W. <hi>having obtained (as he hath ſuggeſted) the Art and Knowledge of making Salt-water of the Sea Freſh</hi>— Calling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Queſtion His Majeſties Teſtimony; yet however, the laſt of thoſe very Articles runs thus—Item, <hi>The ſaid William Walcot doth Covenant and Promiſe, to and with the ſaid</hi> Robert Fitz-Gerald, Theophilus Oglethorp, William Bridgman, Patrick Traunt <hi>and</hi> Thomas Maule, <hi>and every of them, That in Caſe by his Skill and Knowledge in the ſaid Art, found out by the ſaid Patentees, that may make the Operation of Freſhning Sea Water more Eaſy, Commodious or Profitable, He ſhall at all Times upon Requeſt of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees inform and inſtruct them, or any of them therein, and give his Aſſiſtance in all manner of wars to the Promoting the Intereſt, and Profit of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees in relation to the ſaid Art.</hi>— And in a Propoſal diſpatched <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 2d, 1684. they ſay thus— <hi>Upon Condition that He the ſaid</hi> W. Walcot <hi>ſhall Joyn with the Patontees both his Skill and Endeavours</hi> — So that though they are pleaſed to Stile his Art but only his Suggeſtions, yet it is ſuch, that They think neceſſary He ſhould inſtruct them in.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <note place="margin">14. The King granted a Patent to Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> and others, to oppoſe which, Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> entered a Caveat; and after a full hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Council learned on both ſides, the Patent of <hi>Walcot</hi> was laid aſide, and a Patent grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Here they Jumble together confuſedly, to be done as they Pretend at Once, what was done in a great Diſtance of Time, for they had Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained two diſtinct Hearings near Five Months aſunder; the former before the Lord Keeper <hi>North,</hi> to have their Bill paſs the Great Seal; the latter before his Majeſty and his Councel, to Vacate <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent, ſo that the Caveat was entered to ſtop their Bill, many Months before <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent was on Condition Vacated.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97399:7"/>
            <p>Hereby alſo they would make the world believe that <hi>W. W.</hi> had no Patent when their Patent was granted, that they might thereby create ſome Pretence, if it had not been then in Being. But Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>'s Patent was granted near five Months before <hi>W. W.</hi>'s patent was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be made void; for Mr. <hi>Fitz-Geralds</hi> Bill paſſed the Broad Seal, and was thereby made a Patent, <hi>June</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the year 1683 at the Lord Keepers; but <hi>W. W.</hi>'s Patent was not ordered to be made void till at the Hearing in Council on the 30th of <hi>October</hi> following, in 1683; ſo that till this time the Patent of <hi>Walcot was not laid aſide,</hi> as they are pleaſed to term it.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <note place="margin">15. To us the ſaid Patentees.</note> Here Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> would again bring in the Lord <hi>Falkland</hi> to be one of the five Patentees, for the honour of their pretended Invention, who was not, as was ſaid before, one of the five Patentees, but came in unto them long after, to be of their Party. When his Lordſhip came to underſtand arightly the Affair, he was diſſatisfied in their Proceedings, and hath ſince given <hi>W. W.</hi> good aſſurance in his life time, that he would not countenance their Intereſt againſt him; and others have done the like. And he hopes that none (whatever their concerns are) will, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him, maintain a wrong.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <note place="margin">16. Which hath been ſince put in practice both at Sea</note> Many Tryals were made at Sea, but by the ſeeing the proof of them, they were left off and their Skill ſo much Rejected, or to uſe their own Term, <hi>laid aſide,</hi> as it is. It was made appear by many Witneſſes before the Committee, that the Perſons who had dealt with them, and bought their Inſtruments, and were at the Charge of Fixing them to put them in Practice, loſt their Money, being wholly deceived in their Expectation. At the ſame ſitting of the Committee, when their Work and the Practice of it came into queſtion, Mr. <hi>Fitz-G.</hi> applyed himſelf to Sir <hi>M. A.</hi> Member of the Committee there preſent, Telling Him that He had Bought of their Engines, and asked Him to give His Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to the Committee of their Working; This being urged ſeveral Times without Notice taken, at laſt was Anſwered thus, or to this Effect. I do wonder Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> That you ſhould Chooſe to Ask me to Give an Account, for I doubt I ſhall ſay little to your Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I bought ſeveral of your Engines which coſt me <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Pounds, and ſet them to work all at my own Charge, but my Money was all Thrown away— and more to that Purpoſe. This Diſappointment made the Committee very ſenſible of their Skill, and to Obſerve how they had managed their Affairs.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <note place="margin">17. and Land.</note> At <hi>Sheerneſs</hi> Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> and his Partners, had put up their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, which worked there for ſome time, for which it hath been ſaid, they Received from the Tower large Sums of Money, having put the Crown to very Great Expences.</p>
            <p>But after their Water had been much Experienced there, the Work was Diſcontinued, and bath bene left off ever ſince, it being now ſince it had been their carryed on many years, what the Lord <hi>Dartmouth</hi> his Judgment and Account giving of it was, may be ſeen by the following Certiſicate.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavit">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I do hereby Certify, that I was at the Board of Ordnance, when Mr.</hi> Walcot <hi>was ſent for in by the Lord</hi> Dartmouth, <hi>who then Taſted of his Water, and Declared his Approbation of it, and that He had formerly given his Opponents Countenance to ſet up their Work at</hi> Sheerneſs, <hi>but now He had found that their Water was not good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Witneſs my hand,
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Cha. Bertie,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>H. Alured.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Febr.</hi> 10th, 1692.</date>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning their Water prepared in <hi>Lothbury,</hi> at the end of <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mewlane.</hi> See the following Account.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97399:7"/>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavit">
                  <body>
                     <p>I <hi>do certifie that I had ſome of Mr.</hi> Fitz Gerald<hi>'s Water from his Office in</hi> Lothbury, <hi>which I found to be ill taſted, and having kept it by me for Tryal, in a few Months it putrified, grew thick and green, to which I ſubſcribe my Hand,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Clarkenwell-Green</hi> 
                           <date>the 15th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1692.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>W. Savage.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>M.</hi> upon Examination before the Committee, gave an account that he went with Dr. <hi>Fielding</hi> to <hi>Lothbury,</hi> at the end of <hi>Barhtholomew-Lane,</hi> on purpoſe to try Mr. <hi>Fitz.-Gerald</hi>'s Water prepared there, and they found it to be of an ill taſte and ſmell, fiery, harſh and corroding, and not wholeſome for the Body of Man.</p>
            <p>And it is now well known, that their Work and Engine at the Garriſon at <hi>Hull,</hi> the only place perhaps where then it was ſuffered to be, which they made ſuch Oſtentation of in the Seſſion of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 1692. was then found fault with, and ſoon after openly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked, and run into the contempt of many, where they have put Their Majeſties to great Charge, which there was little occaſion for; when better Water might be had not far from the place, or by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying the True Inventor.</p>
            <p>They ſtifly inſiſted (at the Committees) on their Work there, to prevent the paſſing of <hi>W. W.</hi> his Bill, as an Argument that they would ſoon after themſelves highly Advance the Practice of the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Publick Benefit, but the whole Year after in 1693. they had done nothing further worth the taking notice of, which ſeems, when this Matter is conſidered, a Reaſon ſufficient of it ſelf, that they ſhould be no longer hearkened unto.</p>
            <p>And now when their Work hath been ſo often rejected at Sea, and ſometimes on Land, rather then give it utterly off, they again at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to ſet up their Work at Land, in ſuch places where they may be paid by Their Majeſties for their Engines, and the Work be done at Their Majeſties Charge. Preſently after the Seſſion of Parliament in the Year 1692. wherein <hi>W. W.</hi> had his Bill paſſed the Houſe of Commons, and the Committee of the Lords; an Order came from the Council. That the Invention of making Sea-water freſh and wholeſome, (<hi>viz.</hi> Two Engines for the ſame,) ſhould be ſet up at the Iſles of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Gurneſey,</hi> this Order Mr. <hi>Fitz-G.</hi> and his Partners got into their Hands and brought to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and let it lie dormant, neglecting to proceed upon it about a Year, from 1692. till <hi>March</hi> 1693 when <hi>VV. VV.</hi> brought in his Bill again to the Houſe of Lords, and was read; but then they move to get an Order from the Board of Ordnance upon the Order of Council to the end, that they might make a preſent advantage, they receiving 400 <hi>l.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Money, and that by the Pretence and Reputation of being imployed, and up held in Their Majeſties Service, they may for the future prevent <hi>W. W.</hi> his gaining an Act of Parliament, vainly hoping thereby to force <hi>VV. VV.</hi> to diſcover to them the Secrets of his Art, that they might for ever ſupplant him of his Right.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <note place="margin">18 To the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all Perſons.</note> By what they have done, and hath been already ſaid, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that moſt Perſons are ſatisfied what the extent of their skill is, the Seamen, and Phyſicians, and others whom they themſelves have appealed to, having rejected their Work, and Foreigners as well as thoſe of this Nation, and after ſuch Tryals made; To have it rejected, there can be no hopes left, that they withtheir Work ſhould be ever received.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97399:8"/>
            <p>If in eleven years and a half, that they have already had their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent granted to them, and they having <hi>given the most Publick Notice they can of the uſefulneſs of their Invention,</hi> and had the liberty to do what they pleaſed without being obſtructed; this be the Progreſs they have made, and the heigth of the Practice they have brought their Invention to, <hi>viz.</hi> To have one Engine at the Garriſon at <hi>Hull</hi> yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining there not pluckt down, and one for each of the Iſlands of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Guerneſey</hi> but newly ſet up, this will hardly conduce to the ſatisfaction of all Perſons whoſe expectations they have raiſed. And what ſatisfaction can they give to all Perſons for depriving them by ſuch practice of the benefit of <hi>W. W.</hi> his Art all this while, which ought to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>And what can it avail them, to bring any late Certificates of their skill to ſhew now: when it is viſible they perform the Work no better, nor in other manner than they have done formerly; neither do they petend to more skill now than heretofore, for they have this very year propoſed and contracted to make their Work at <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Guernſey,</hi> anſwerable only to what they have done otherwhere, and no otherwiſe, and undertaken to Inſtruct Perſons to Work according to the ſame manner only, as they have ſhewn to do it long ago.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <note place="margin">19 Who have not been inſtuenced by their particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</note> If their Work had proved according to their Pretences, and the expectation they had raiſed, People might have perhaps been influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by their particular Intereſts to have received it; but particular Intereſts could not have Influenced the World to throw it off, if once it had been well received upon Proofs.</p>
            <p>This they venture to ſay when they well know the Houſe of Commons did utterly diſallow of their Practice and Art both at Sea and Land, and that alſo the Committee of the Lords were but little ſatisfied therein.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <note place="margin">20 There being a Bill brought in by the ſaid Mr. <hi>VValcot</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>W. W.</hi> having firſt obtained leave, brought his Bill into the Houſe of Commons, and had good Reaſon to do it, ſeeing the Law doth greatly countenance new Inventions, taking a particular care that they may be preſerved. Wherefore the very Statute in the 21ſt. year of King <hi>James</hi> the I. made againſt Monoplies <hi>(which are miſchievous to the State by raiſing Prizes of Commodities at home, or hurt of Trades, or generally inconvenient)</hi> doth in an eſpecial manner, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide that new Inventions may be encouraged; therein declaring the King's Power to grant his Letters Patents for ſuch: And oftentimes by Act of Parliament, the ſole Benefit of a new Invention hath been granted to the firſt Inventor for a long term of years, as ſometimes for thirty one years, and ſometimes given to the Inventor and his Heirs, as being no way miſchievous to the State, but the product of his own Induſtry for the Publick Good. The Houſe paſſed <hi>W. W.</hi> his Dill, wherein all Perſons are wholly left to their Liberty, whether they will make uſe of his Invention or not.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <note place="margin">21 To deſtroy the Right of our Patent.</note> Their Patent never had any Right, by reaſon that at the time when their Patent paſſed the Broad-Seal, which was <hi>June</hi> 1683. there was a former Patent dated in <hi>October</hi> 1675. granted to <hi>W. W.</hi> then in Being, declaring that His Majeſty had ſeen <hi>evident Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of W. VV.</hi> his Art, as hath been mentioned; beſides there are able Lawyers, that ſay His Majeſty had Power to grant a Patent but once for the ſame Invention, and their Patent was gained but by ſpecious Pretences, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>VV. VV.</hi> had made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, and had utterly diſerted the buſineſs (which now might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted truly upon them <hi>ut antea:</hi>) Whereas he had endeavored, both in Town and Country with all his power conſtantly to advance it, being
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97399:8"/>employed in having Inſtruments compleated of Caſt Iron that would file, ſuch as himſelf had Invented, and all ſorts of Materials made up proper for Ships, when all Workmen were unexperienced therein, and was extreamly delayed by long attending the then Lords Commiſſioners of the Admiralty, for a Ship to ſet up his Work in, and could not procure any from them at all, or otherwhere, till he had agreed upon a price to buy one; at which time Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> with his Partners aroſe up, whereby he was prevented, who have obſtructed him ever ſince. They likewiſe alledged that they could perform the Work better than <hi>W. W.</hi> the True Inventor, which hath ſince appeared both in reſpect of the Water and way of Operation notoriouſly otherwiſe. But if they or any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould have attained to <hi>W. W.</hi> his Art, after he had made ſuch Evident Demonſtrations before ſo many Perſons, and in the preſence of <hi>Such Teſtimony,</hi> and had alſo publickly formed, and made large Proviſion of Inſtruments and other Materials for the Work, none elſe can in Juſtice ever be accounted the Proprietors without him, or take the Advantages from him.</p>
            <p>Neither had their Patent any Right, becauſe Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners were not the firſt Inventor, who knew not the Art at the time when firſt it was found out, which Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners could not pretend to, but have acknowledged the contrary; nay, he is ſo far from being the firſt Inventor, that he hath ſhewn, and it iappears by his Tryals, and Proofs that he hath not yet attained to the True uſeful Art.</p>
            <p n="22">22 <note place="margin">22 In which there are about five Years unexpired.</note> Their Patent was dated <hi>June</hi> 1683. So that in leſs than Two Years and an half, the Fourteen Years therein expreſſed, will be ended; but ſince their Patent was thus wrongfully begun and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully carried on ever ſince, as is proved, no time can remain unexpired.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <note place="margin">23 It is therefore</note> By reaſon of ſo many unwarrantable Suggeſtions.</p>
            <p n="24">24 <note place="margin">24 Humbly prayed the ſaid Bill may not paſs</note> They did thus humbly pray the Houſe of Commons by their Petition, that they <hi>be admitted at the Bar of this Houſe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Committee thereof, to offer their Reaſons.</hi> (See what they were, <hi>pag.</hi> 3.) <hi>Against the intended Bill, and that they may be allowed the Benefit of an Act to themſelves</hi>—To enable them to do what by their pretended skill, they cannot, to practice the Art, they did not underſtand; and to exclude him that invented the Art. Which Petition was committed with the Bill, ſo that there was no danger of their being ſurprized, when what was ordered, was according to their own Petition, yet when the Committee ſate, they were not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to appear without further Summons, but contrived delays, as much as poſſibly they could; and when the Committee had given them long time of Summons, Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> came without his Council, alleadging that his Council were not mentioned in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <note place="margin">25 To the Prejudice of the ſaid Letters Patents of Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> and his Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> The paſſing of the Bill could not have been to the prejudice of their Letters Patents, ſeeing they were not grounded upon any Right as is already proved; nor to themſelves ſince they never had attained to the true Art, nor could longer propoſe ever to do themſelves any good by their own; wherefore it is manifeſt they would rather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſuppreſs the Art, than not be themſelves the Maſters and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers of it. And becauſe they cannot force <hi>VV. VV.</hi> to comply ſo far with them, as to inſtruct them in the Secrets of his Art to undo himſelf, they are inveterate againſt him, thence ſtilling him a Perſon refractory; making themſelves by their oppoſing him, both Acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Principals to all the Misfortunes that ſhall ever happen in the World, through the want of the Exerciſe of the true Art.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97399:9"/>
            <p n="26">26 <note place="margin">26 The ſaid Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Here they not truſting to all their preceding matter, ſtart from it to that of another kind.</p>
            <p>If they mean hereby that Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> conſented to the getting out their Patent, the contrary is Apparent: For he had Addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Lord Keeper <hi>North,</hi> to oppoſe the paſſing of their Bill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Broad Seal, and entered (as Mr. <hi>Fitz</hi>-G. acknowledgeth) a Caveat likewiſe that it ſhould not paſs him unwittingly. See <hi>p. 7.</hi> And this <hi>W. W.</hi> made his eſpecial care to prevent, and by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel withſtood it all he could.</p>
            <p>Neither had he agreed ever to impart to them his skill without the knowledge of which his right could not be transferred by him to them.</p>
            <p>Neither did he ever Seal or enter into any Articles with them.</p>
            <p n="27">27 <note place="margin">27 Under them.</note> Neither did he ever give his conſent to any Agreement to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to be under them (which therefore they can never produce as they pretended they were ready to do) he having by his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry atchieved and become an abſolute Maſter of his Art, would not ſubmit his skill to come under them who were ignorant of it.</p>
            <p>So that there was never any Agreement made with them that they can pretend to, otherwiſe than a ſhort Writing meerly in order to a Treaty, or that he and they ſhould Treat, which in ſome Sence may be called an Agreement, as being in order thereunto: He and they agreeing only ſo far, That they ſhould by a tendering of Articles (to each other) endeavour to make an Agreement (though ſuch Agreement could never be effected;) and that was yielded to on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grounds quite different from what they would Repreſent, and made to other Purpoſes, and cannot bear any ſuch meaning as what they urge but quite the contrary, as would have appeared by the Writing if they had produced it, which they kept in their own Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody from the time it was Wrote, and would never ſuffer <hi>W. W.</hi> to have a ſight of it ever ſince, which they were pleaſed much to inſiſt upon, neither would they produce it at any ſitting of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, though they were urged to it, leaſt it might detect their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Dealing. And therefor e of the Writing, and how it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, it is neceſſary there ſhould be ſome Account given.</p>
            <p>At the time that they brought <hi>W. W.</hi> a Summons to appear before the Lord Keeper, to the end that their Bill might be made a Patent (in or about <hi>April</hi> in the Year, 1683.) there was ſomething written on a Scrip of Paper, in Order as was ſaid be fore, to a Treaty, the Subſtance whereof was, That all things ſhould ſtand in the ſame Condition and Plight as they were at that time as to the Title, <hi>viz.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi>'s Patent ſhould remain, and that their Bill ſhould be ſtopped, and that no further endeavours ſhould be uſed to have it paſs the Great Seal. That Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> with his Partners ſhould have a very conſiderable part granted by Articles to be agreed on out of the profits of Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> his Patent <hi>for ſeven years yet to come,</hi> (from the time the Writing was made) in caſe other Covenants ſhould be likewiſe Propoſed, and in caſe ſuch ſhould be agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that all Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi>'s Charges and Expences ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted, which he valued at, and at that time demanded for, four Thouſand Pounds.</p>
            <p>This Writing to the end that <hi>W. W.</hi> might be ſure to prevent their Bill ever to be made a Patent, he contented himſelf to comply with, and proceeded according to the Contents of it, deſiſting from his uſual way of Proceedings, in Advancing his own Concern ſolely for himſelf, and on the occaſion thereof endeavoured to bring the matter to a perfect Accommodation between them, by delaying his work
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97399:9"/>waiting for, and taking into conſideration their Articles which they a while after tendered (though his Councel thought not fit he ſhould allow of them becauſe of their unreaſonableneſs: ſome further Account is given of them, <hi>pag.</hi> 15.) and then by offering Articles that himſelf had cauſed to be drawn in Purſuance of that Writing, performing on his part according to the Contents thereof whatſoever it required of him; wherein <hi>W. W.</hi> propoſed to give Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> and the other Patentees each of them ſuch a part out of the profits of his Patent, as the Writing had mentioned, as may appear by thoſe Articles, which Articles were by them rejected. By the tendering of thoſe Articles <hi>VV. VV.</hi> hath reaſon to believe he had diſcharged himſelf from <hi>the Writing,</hi> they having had the Effects of it; and that he was no way obliged further, when they had rejected ſuch Articles as were drawn by Eminent Counſel upon conſideration of the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, conformable thereunto.</p>
            <p>But ſoon after the Writing was made, and before Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> had brought in his intended Articles, an Advertiſement was put into the Gazette, that <hi>Robert Fitz Gerald</hi> Eſquire, and ſome other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men had found out the Art of Reducing Salt Water of the Sea into perfect and wholeſome Freſh Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> withot <hi>VV. VV.</hi> his Name or Conſent. Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> and the other Patentees on their part, notoriouſly brake this their Agreement (as they call it) by their acting ſeperately from <hi>VV. VV.</hi> in carrying on their Deſign without him; in applying to the Phyſicians for their Hands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him; or acquainting him with it by publiſhing a Book to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance themſelves and to obſtruct him; wherein Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to give an Account who the Gentlemen concerned were, (wherein there is no mention of <hi>VV. VV.</hi> at all) who do intend to agree with all ſuch as are willing to deal with them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by their further oppoſing him from time to time.</p>
            <p>And they alſo brake this their Agreement, by their taking out their Patent <hi>June</hi> 1683. <hi>Which Patent (as that Writing expreſſed) is now Paſſing the Great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>but ſtop'd there by a Caveat entered by the ſaid Mr.</hi> Walcot (which Bill, after the Writing was ſubſcribed, was alſo ſtopped by themſelves by force, they ſaid, of that Agreement) ſo by getting out their Patent, they put Things in another Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Plight, than they were in at the time of the making of the Writing; whereas to have all things kept in the ſame condition as they were then in, was the chief Cauſe and Conſideration of <hi>W. W.</hi> his yielding thereunto, as is manifeſt by the Preamble: And therein they impugned his Right and the Title by his Patent (as ſince they have done before His Majeſty and his Council) which was Paramount, and the Foundation, on which this Writing did depend, and an eſſential Part, which according to the Writing they ought to have Acquieſced in.</p>
            <p>And (on the 30th. of <hi>October,</hi> in the ſame Year 1683.) by their procuring his Patent to be vacated (it being the Title which by that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, they were neceſſarily to come under,) they did not only break this their Agreement, but abſolutely put an end to it, wholly deſtroying it in the Foundation; by making thereby their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment utterly impoſſible to be performed; becauſe as was ſaid before, when this Writing was made, they could no otherwiſe derive any Title to the Profits, but by <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent; as appears by the Writing, and the time it was made; and alſo becauſe <hi>W. W.</hi> his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was an eſſential Part of it. And the Vacating of the Patent muſt neceſſarily determine any ſuch Agreement which related there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and wholly depended thereon. <hi>So that by the very Order that</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97399:10"/>W. W. <hi>his Patent ſhould be made void, and that the Agreement ſhould be Performed:</hi> The Agreement (according to the ſame Agreement) was made void and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>The Order for Vacating of his Patent, they had brought about and effected in Council, by their having miſinformed His Majeſty and His Council concerning the Writing; by rendering it to the Council in a Senſe quite otherwiſe than the True Senſe that was manifeſtly intended therein, or what it could poſſibly bear (as by the other Contents may be ſeen) to be the Meaning; altering and perverting the Senſe, and not only wreſting the Senſe, but the very Words too out of their Places, by their miſrepreſenting the Matter in evaſive Words, varying from the Writing, inſomuch that His Majeſty's Order by their means, was made upon a wrong Ground, as will appear by the Recital of that part of the Writing that is in the Order, if compared, it palpably differing from, if not directly contrary to the Writing. And the next Words following in the Order are, <hi>His Majeſty thought ſit the ſaid Agreement ſhould be performed;</hi> and ſo the latter part of the Order after the Recital, by their means runs all along upon wrong Suppoſitions. And <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent was declared, <hi>ſhould be made void, as being inconvenient to His Majeſty's Subjects,</hi> that theirs might take place upon their pretending to the ſame Invention, as convenient.</p>
            <p>According to the Account they gave of the Words of the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they were theſe as recited in the Order—<hi>The ſaid Mr.</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot <hi>is to be allowed a ſixth Part of the clear Profits ariſing by the Practice of the ſaid Art, after all Charges and Expences about the ſame ſhall be deducted</hi>—Let us ſee how Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> makes this out. To be allowed by whom? <hi>By Mr.</hi> Fitz-Gerald <hi>and his Partners.</hi> Out of what? <hi>Out of the clear Profits ariſing by the Practice of Mr.</hi> Fitz-Gerald<hi>'s Art.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Eitz</hi> G. and his Partners could not allow any thing ſo ariſing from the Practice of their Art, for they had not any Right, as firſt Inventor, nor had, when the Writing was made, a Patent, nor had then the Art, as they have ſince given full Evidence, that they never had. Why then if Mr. <hi>Fitz</hi> G. hath no Right as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor, nor gotten the Art himſelf; he can however allow to Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> a ſixth Part of the clear Profits ariſing out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi>'s own Art, Mr. <hi>Fitz</hi> G. reſerving the other five Parts of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> his Art to himſelf and his Partners—But beſides that Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> hath no Right to <hi>W. W.</hi> his Art, he doth not know his Art, and then how can he allow to <hi>W. W.</hi> clear Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits ariſing by the Practice of the Art, he did not underſtand him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> hath obtained his own Patent to paſs the Seal, notwithſtanding the <hi>Caveat,</hi> and the Writing made to prevent it, and hath procured <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent to be vacated, and will bring him to comply, and to inſtruct him in his Art, and if <hi>W. W.</hi> will not, with the King's Order he will force him. But Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> was ſhrewdly miſtaken in this, the King would never Order that <hi>W. W.</hi> ſhould be forced to impart to Mr. <hi>Fitz</hi> G. his Secrets, and to teach him his Art, who His Majeſty knew had ſo difficultly attained to it, by his own Charge and Induſtry, and Perfected it by His Majeſty's Special Command; and then when <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent was ordered to be Vacated, <hi>W. W.</hi> could not himſelf Proceed, and ſo Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> could have no Profits that way, nor any thing to ſettle or diſpoſe of, ariſing from the Practice of the Art in any manner. Yet though no ſuch thing was mentioned in the Order, Mr. <hi>Fitz</hi> G. however hoped therewith to affright him into a Diſcovery of the Secrets of his Art to him.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97399:10"/>
            <p>Where it is ſaid in the Order, <hi>after all Charges and Expences about the ſame ſhall be deducted,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> would have it intended that all his own Charges ſhould be allowed to him, and to the other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees theirs; but that none of <hi>W. W.</hi> his Charges ſhould be allowed to him whatever theſe have amounted to, and how much ſoever theſe have exceeded all theirs.</p>
            <p>By the next Words following in the Order, <hi>viz. His Majesty thought fit the ſaid Agreement ſhould be Performed.</hi> It appears His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had been made believe that <hi>W. W.</hi> had not Performed what the Contents of the Writing had required, or had done any thing that might diſcharge himſelf from it. See <hi>pag.</hi> 13. What <hi>W. W.</hi> had performed; which if His Majeſty had known, 'tis not to be imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that he ever would have condeſcended to ſuch an Order; But Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners ſucceeded herein, by reaſon that <hi>W. W.</hi> had not inſtructed his Counſel in any thing concerning the aforementioned Writing, ſince it could not be expected, that they would have, before His Majeſty and His Council, inſiſted on that which <hi>W.W.</hi> had ſo diſcharged himſelf of, and they had departed from long before, and had acted ſo contrary thereunto. See <hi>pag.</hi> 13. Neither did they mention it, till they found that not any thing they had alleadged, could avail them; when His Majeſty himſelf had defended <hi>W. W.</hi> his Cauſe, and had anſwered their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</p>
            <p>It appears that beſides a wrong Account given concerning the Writing, upon which the Order was made, it was granted alſo upon the Preſumption, that Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners had gained the True Art, elſe it could not poſſibly have been yielded unto; which proving otherwiſe, His Majeſty was in that reſpect alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in His Grant.</p>
            <p>Yet, notwithſtanding all this, His Majeſty declared at that time in Council, that his Inclinations then were to Grant again to <hi>W. W.</hi> Solely His Letters Patents, for Fourteen Years, if he had Power to do it. Then being put in mind that he had newly granted to Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners a Patent; His Majeſty preſently intended that <hi>W. W.</hi> ſhould enjoy the Benefit of Fourteen Years from thence, which was the Reaſon that Prevailed with His Majeſty to yield to that Order. But they contrary to His Majeſty's Gracious Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Royal Pleaſure, by that means would take Advantage to thruſt him out of all.</p>
            <p>The Words of the Order which they thus obtained are—<hi>That Mr.</hi> Walcot<hi>'s Patent ſhould be made void, as being inconvenient to His Majesty's Subjects, and the Petitioners are by their Inſtrument to ſettle a ſixth Part upon the ſaid Mr.</hi> Walcot, <hi>according to the ſaid Agreement, and if the Parties differ, they are to attend the Attorney General, who is to ſettle the Conveyances between them</hi>—So that they were not to attend the Attorney General till the Petitioners had firſt tendered to <hi>W. W.</hi> their <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of Settlement, and that then they could not agree; which they never did at any time offer, nor any part of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to this day: But inſtead of making a Settlement, or bringing any Profit, they only tendered moſt unreaſonable Articles for him to ſign, the ſame which he had rejected before they had their Patent; and afterwards they tendered thoſe more enlarged for their Intereſt, and ſeveral new ones were added to them, whereby he could not but have been inevitably ruined, if they could have inviegled him to have ſubſcribed them, for thereby he had made himſelf many Thouſand of Pounds worſe than nothing; but he never ſubſcribed to thoſe, or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97399:11"/>to any Articles of theirs, as hath been already ſaid; the Recital of a ſmall part of one of their Articles is enough to evidence this,— <hi>That there ſhall ſome able and ſit Perſon be elected and appointed by the ſaid Parties to theſe Preſents, or the major Number of them, whereof always the ſaid</hi> Robert Fitz-Gerald, <hi>his Deputy or Aſſign to be one to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend—in nature of a Clerk, or Register who ſhall be Authorized— under the Hands and Seals of the major part of them, whereof always the ſaid</hi> Robert Fitz-Gerald, <hi>his Deputy or Aſſign to be one—who ſhall keep one or more Book or Books—and ſhall in ſuch Book or Books, enter down all ſuch Votes as they the ſaid Parties, or the major Number of them ſhall agree upon. Which Votes being entered down and ſigned by the ſaid Parties to theſe Preſents, or the major number of them; whereof always the ſaid</hi> Robert Fitz-Gerald, <hi>his Deputy or Aſſign to be one, ſhall be as obliging to them the ſaid Parties, and every of them, as if the ſaid Votes and Reſolutions were contained in theſe Preſents</hi>—So that they might from time to time impoſe whatever Sums of Money they pleaſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>VV. VV.</hi> to pay. In the ſame manner all Servants and Officers he would have to be choſen, and ſuch as ſhall go into Foreign Parts, or be otherwiſe employed for promoting the ſaid Concern, ſhall have ſuch Allowance as the major Number of them, whereof always the ſaid <hi>Robert Fitz Gerald,</hi> his Deputy or Aſſign to be one, ſhall think fit and appoint. This Clauſe (whereof always the ſaid <hi>Robert Fitz Gerald,</hi> his Deputy or Aſſign to be one) put in the latter Articles which they tendered, ſometimes is introduced three or four times in an Article, which Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi> aſſumed from thoſe Articles that <hi>VV. VV.</hi> had formerly propoſed to him; and changed the Name for his; Inſerting his own Name in the place of <hi>W. W.</hi> This Clauſe was abſolutely neceſſary for <hi>W. W.</hi> to uſe (he being the only Perſon in the Articles on the one part, and they being five on the other) the better to ſecure himſelf from any unjuſt Impoſitions; but very improper, and moſt unfit for Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> to appropriate to himſelf, and to take the advantage of, without any to counterpoiſe him; whereby <hi>W. W.</hi> ſhould have been wholly expoſed to their Arbitrement and Mercy. Another Article is this—Item, <hi>The ſaid</hi> William Walcot <hi>doth Covenant to and with the ſaid Patentees and every of them, that he the ſaid</hi> William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot, <hi>his Executors and Administrators ſhall advance and pay in one full ſixth part of all ſuch Charges, Disburſements, and Expences, as have been already, or hereafter ſhall be laid out, or expended in or about the Premiſes, before and until ſufficient do, in by the Art and Miſtery to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray the Charges of the ſame.</hi> Under this Head, he would have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and comprized ſo many Editions of his Books, that he ſent over the World to obſtruct <hi>W. W.</hi> his Proceedings; and to make a City Feaſt, and ſuch like. This was the uſe they would have made of His Majeſty's Order.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> and his Partners had found that <hi>W. W.</hi> had upon the Demonſtrations of his Art, obtained Letters Patents from the States General, and other from the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> whereby their Services were rejected, and themſelves excluded; And when <hi>VV. VV.</hi> was in <hi>Holland,</hi> they made this further Propoſal.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97399:11"/>
               <head>2d. December 84.</head>
               <p>REſolved, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Bridgman <hi>with two or three more of the Patentees or Commiſſioners, do wait upon Sir</hi> Thomas Walcot <hi>and ſhew to him the Readineſs of the
<note place="margin">(a) They had reaſon to be ready ſince <hi>VV. VV.</hi> had a Patent ſeven Years before theirs.</note> Patentees to take into their
<note place="margin">(b) What their readineſs was to obey King <hi>Charles</hi> his Order, they ſhew in their Propoſing the following Conditions as well as their former.</note> Partnerſhip his Brother</hi> William Walcot <hi> Eſq if he will recede from his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings abroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they will admit him to a full
<note place="margin">(c) <hi>Viz.</hi> A ſixth part of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his own Art, reſerving the other five parts for themſelves.</note> ſixth Part of the whole, as well for
<note place="margin">(d) All the World over which they herein are pleaſed to aſſume to themſelves, and to pretend a Title to, though they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>Holland</hi> and all the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions thereto belonging.</note> all Foreign Parts, as for His Majeſties Dominions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he ſhall have a
<note place="margin">(e) Of what effect it were for <hi>W. W.</hi> to have one Vote amongſt them all, is already ſaid. <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</note> Vote and all Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges as any one of the
<note place="margin">(f) When they themſelves had not juſtly any Rights or Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges therein.</note> Patentees, upon Condition that he the ſaid</hi> William Walcot <hi>ſhall joyn with the Patentees both his
<note place="margin">(g) Whereby it appears they found it neceſſary for themſelves to have the benefit of theſe.</note> skill and endeavour for the
<note place="margin">(h) They would enjoyn <hi>VV. VV.</hi> with his skill to endeavour the general Good of the Concern in all Foreign Parts, by receding from his Proceedings abroad.</note> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral good of the concern; and that the drawing up the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to this Effect be referred to
<note place="margin">(i) Who drew their Bill when <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent was on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and who was after their Council to defend it.</note> Mr. Attorney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This their Propoſal <hi>W. W.</hi> did not think fit to admit of.</p>
               <p n="28">28. <note place="margin">28 As will be ready to be produced.</note> After all the ſtir they made about being ready to ſhew an Agreement, they did not produce any, either before the Committees of the Commons, or of the Lords, (although often preſſed thereto) as hath been ſaid; ſo that what Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners moſt injuriouſly would have ſuggeſted, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>W. W.</hi> had given up his Right to them, they could no way make out before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees.</p>
               <p>The Year after that ſuch Agreement as they pretend was made, and after they had procured their Patent, Dat. <hi>June</hi> 1683. And the Order of Counſel in <hi>October</hi> next following, and when <hi>VV. VV.</hi> had taken his Voyage into <hi>Holland,</hi> having heard in <hi>England</hi> that they were then endeavouring to gain a Patent there alſo, a Writing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97399:12"/>was produced in <hi>Holland</hi> that began thus.—<hi>De Heeren</hi> Rob. Fitz Gerald, Col. Theophil. Oglethorp <hi>neffens hunne undere ge aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erden hebbende Conſt bevorden Zee water andere brack water tot ſout wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te Maecken bequaem om te Drincken,</hi> &amp;c.—Tranſlated thus, The Gentlemen <hi>Robert Fitz-Gerald,</hi> Col. <hi>Theop. Oglethorpe</hi> with the reſt of their Aſſociates, having found out the Art of making Sea, and brackiſh Water wholeſome, and fit to Drink,—<hi>Deputeers een afgeſonden Mr.</hi> Wilhelmus Fitz-Gerald <hi>een vande gejntereſſeerde</hi> — Deputed and ſent Mr. <hi>VVilliam Fitz-Gerald</hi> a Perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed therein—who did in the Year, 1684 give in this Writing from them to the States, wherein they attempted extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vilifie both <hi>VV. VV.</hi> himſelf and his Art, therein they ſay, — <hi>Het is waer dat een Genaemt VValcot die geene intereſt met Genaem Hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren en heeft geprétendeert dat hij de voors Conſt Hadden gevonden.</hi>— It is true, that there is a Perſon named <hi>VValcot,</hi> who is not concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the above named Gentlemen, hath pretended to be the finder out of the ſaid Art,—ſo that they renounce any pretence to any agreement, and thereby alſo they ſhewed, they did abſolutely Contemn and Reject His Majeſties Order in Counſel, which had enjoyned them to be concerned with that <hi>VValcot</hi> in their making their <hi>Intrument</hi> of Settlement upon him, the Order having been granted them and declared to be on that very Condition; See the words of the Order before recited page 15. which it was manifeſt hereby that they were reſolved not to Obſerve. And in the ſame Writing, they gave an unwarrantable Account of the Proceedings of the Counſel in this Affair, and accuſed <hi>VV. VV.</hi> as a Criminal in theſe Words,— <hi>Siine Majeſte Van Gr. Brita. door beſtuijt van Siien Rect van ſtacten de brieuven van Octroy aen voorn VValcot geaccordeert beeft ingetrocken ende te niet Gedaen, om dat hij Strijdick was tegons de VVetten van En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geland ende tegens de Goede Zeeden;</hi> — His Majeſty of great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with the Advice of his Privy Counſel, hath nullified and drawn in the Letters Patents granted to the ſaid <hi>VValcot,</hi> becauſe he was Refractory to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and againſt Civil Policy. — And likewiſe, many groundleſs Aſſertions, they would have ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, to magnifie themſelves and their own skill, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from him and his Art, which they could not juſtifie, the matter being extreamly miſrepreſented, as may appear by this foregoing Diſcourſe, wherein thoſe are ſufficiently diſproved.</p>
               <p n="29">29 Mr.
<note place="margin">29 If Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> can obtain an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in Prejudice of this Patent.</note> 
                  <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners brought their Bill into Parliament in the Year 1685. to the end that <hi>VV. VV.</hi> might be Excluded in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that when the ſecrets of his Art ſhould be diſcovered in <hi>Holland,</hi> where he then was, they might be ſure to graſp the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages thereof. To defend his Right therefore he was forced to come abruptly out of <hi>Holland,</hi> and could not return thither ſince to the Publick Exerciſe of his Art.</p>
               <p n="30">30 It ſeems not unreaſonable,
<note place="margin">30 Which ſeems un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable.</note> that he that hazarded his Time, Charge and Labour to Invent an Art ſo Beneficial to Mankind, by denying himſelf the gain that might have ariſen from his other Studies, and through obſervance of His Majeſties eſpecial Command, wholly applyed himſelf to the advancing and bringing it by infinite of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments to Rules of a perfect Art, accompliſhed at his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and grievous Expences, and had alſo given to His Majeſty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Evidence of the Reality thereof, ſhould have at length reaped ſuitable Benefit; but it ſeems very unreaſonable, that others ſhould preſume to ſupplant him after all this was done, to ſnatch from him, and graſp all the advantages to themſelves; when they ought rather to have endeavoured him what ſatisfaction they could for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97399:12"/>the infinite injury they had done him, though to have made him juſt Recompence had been utterly impoſſible, who at laſt, in labouring to cauſe his Bill to be ſtopped, would maintain and juſtifie all their former Wrong by doing Greater.</p>
               <p>It ſeems not at all unreaſonable that thoſe that have thus long obſtructed the true Inventor in the Exerciſe of his Art, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Publick Benefit ſhould be now ordered to Ceaſe.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Mr.
<note place="margin">31 It is hoped it will be with a ſaving to Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi>'s Patent.</note> 
                  <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners had contrived delaies all they could as is before mentioned to the Houſe of Commons, and ſo now they do to the Houſe of Lords. They were always ready to attend till the time came that they were called for, but then were gone aſide, and neglected it, loytering till they might have Summons given, on pretence that they ſhould not be ſurprized, whereas their Petition was committed with the Bill by the Commons, as hath been ſaid, and they were well aware the Bill was paſſed, and could not but know that the Bill was ſent to the Lords. However, the Committee of the Lords Deferred their Proceedings till they might have Summons given them; yet would not Mr. <hi>Fitz-G.</hi> ſubmit to what the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte had done, when they had paſſed the Bill, but Petitioned preſently to the Houſe of Lords, Humbly complaining for want as they pretended of due Summons (though they were given them the day before) that the Bill might be Recommitted which was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and leave was given by the Committe to bring in a <hi>Proviſo</hi> next Morning; which the Lords met on purpoſe (where <hi>VV. VV.</hi> attended by Order) to ſee what it was. But Mr. <hi>Fitz-G.</hi> came without bringing in any <hi>Proviſo,</hi> but inſtead thereof offered to their Lordſhips a Propoſal in Writing, that Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> would allow to Mr. <hi>VValcot</hi> a ſixth Part of the Profits ariſing by the Practice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which could be no other than giving him the ſixth Part ariſing by the Practice of his own Art, which by their Contrivance is nothing whilſt they hinder his Working; and then he would have impoſed this, which their Lordſhips would not meddle with.</p>
               <p>But what Confidence can <hi>VV. VV.</hi> put in thoſe Perſons whoſe Dealings from time to time he hath had this Experience of; his heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning anew to any Propoſal from them, may be ill reſented by all thoſe, who upon his Demonſtrations made, had owned his Cauſe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted his Intereſt. And by thoſe who had known the extent of his Adverſaries skill, and what their Right is, and had rejected both to accept of his; and ſhould draw upon his Art the Cenſures of all the Errors and miſcarriages they have run into by their Inadvertency, and want of Skill; and ſhould by ſuch an interpoſition Eclips the Honour his Art hath juſtly gained, and truſt himſelf to the Fortune of theirs. And what Propoſals can be hearkened unto, or Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can poſſibly be made with them, who took no care to obſerve King <hi>Charles</hi> his Order in Counſel, which was made ſo much to their Advantage; But inſtead of the Uſes His Majeſty intended, inverted it to other ends to thruſt him out of all, inſomuch as a ſixth part of the clear profits that His Majeſty Ordered long ſince in 1683. they would not vouchſafe to ſettle upon him in ſo many Years; but <hi>VV. VV.</hi> hath great Reaſon to believe by the Account the Patentees themſelves, and others have given, that they have received from ſome few Perſons ſuch large Sums for Shares, that long ago not a ſixth part of the whole Gain, according to their own Diviſion and Valuation of it hath been left undiſpoſed of, they having dealt with many; All perhaps made away by their dividing the future profits which might have been raiſed by a Man of skill into Shares, and Selling them; though they had in Truth not any thing themſelves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97399:13"/>to diſpoſe of, having neither Right to the Benefit (as is proved) nor Ability in point of skill to perform the Work, whence the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits ſhould ariſe as by the Event doth appear. Wherefore by their Dealing it is plain, that they had never any intention of obſerving any Agreement with <hi>VV. VV.</hi> but deſigned to involve him in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petnal Delaies and infinite Diſappointments, and by their trifling pretences always to take advantage, and at length to draw him into thoſe deſtructive Articles they had propoſed.</p>
               <p>And it is not now to be expected, neither is it poſſible that ever any Agreement of Partnerſhip can be made with them, unleſs <hi>VV. VV.</hi> ſhould proſtitute himſelf and his Art to the Mercy of their Debts and Humour, by expoſing his Art to be liable to pay all thoſe Shares which they have for great Sums of Money long ago ſold, and ſatally charged upon the Fund of their own Skill. Thoſe ſhares they can never acquit themſelves of, except they can transfer them upon him; ſo that his agreeing with them were no leſs than agreeing that all ſhould be ſwept away from him, beſides himſelf be irrecoverably ruined by their Debts and Impoſitions. And it were very vain to imagine that <hi>VV. VV.</hi> ſhould neglect to diſcharge his Obligations to thoſe that have kindly aſſiſted him, and at the ſame time plunge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under the Burthen of thoſe Perſons Debts that have cruelly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him. That he ſhould allot out of his own Art thoſe ſhares that his Adverſaries have been paid for, or ſhould undertake to repay thoſe Sums of Money his Adverſaries have received for themſelves, and thoſe which perhaps by due, ought to have been his, but were contrarily emploied to cauſe his Expence and to force his Ruine. And it were as vain to imagine he ſhould pay for their being inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Art they never knew, but only pretended to, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might Uſurp his Right who was the true Maſter of it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> hath no Reaſon to delude himſelf, or to trifle <hi>VV. VV.</hi> with ſuch Phantaſies.</p>
               <p>So that upon the whole matter, it is plainly Evident, that Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> and his Partners cannot have any pretence to expect <hi>VV. VV.</hi> ſhould any way comply with them in this Affair, nor to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the paſſing of his Bill by reaſon.</p>
               <p>That <hi>VV. W.</hi> had obtained Letters Patents ſolely to himſelf ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years before they had any Patent.</p>
               <p>That <hi>W. VV.</hi> performed on his part whatever he had agreed to, and that though he agreed that Articles ſhould be offered, which (he having allowed them therein thoſe Advantages they had inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) were tendered accordingly; yet he never entred into Articles of Agreement, ſuch being rejected; ſo that he never gave up his right to them, as they had pretended.</p>
               <p>That <hi>W. W.</hi> the Inventor hath given evident Demonſtrations, and had the Greateſt <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to bear him Witneſs, that he can certainly perform the true Art; But, by what Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Part ners have done, they have ſhewn they have not attained the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but are ignorant of it.</p>
               <p>That their Patent was obtained by wrong, and was wrongfully continued ever ſince.</p>
               <p>That they can take no benefit of the Order of Counſel, by reaſon they never performed the neceſſary condition therein Required. And the King was deceived in his Grant by their miſrepreſenting the matter, neither were they permitted by the order to enjoy their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, or to practice their Art, except they had firſt made their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> of ſettlement upon <hi>W. W.</hi> which they never tendered.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97399:13"/>
               <p n="32">32. <note place="margin">32 That of Mr. <hi>Walcots</hi> being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired as to time.</note> Whether <hi>W. W.</hi> his Patent was expired as to the time, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to the purpoſe, ſince by Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> and his Partners, it had been obſtructed, and by their means ordered to be vacated; for the Prayer of <hi>W.VV.</hi> his Petition to the Houſe of Commons, and the intent of the Bill was, <hi>That</hi> W. W. <hi>might be reſtored to his Right,</hi> (viz. reſtored by having an Act of Parliament, not by having his Old Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in Force again;) <hi>And have his Term which hath been interrupted, renewed, and enlarged;</hi> wherefore his Bill was to renew his Term, as well as to enlarge it; becauſe of their getting a Patent to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their procuring an Order, that his Patent ſhould be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, whereby they obſtructed his Proceedings: So that he having once obtained a Patent, and having before his Patent granted, had the grand Right of an Inventor, which is ſtill ſurviving, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to continue, the Obſtructions of his Right by their procuring a Patent, and by their otherwiſe oppoſing his Patent, and cauſing an Order to vacate it, and the neceſſity of paſſing the Act for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Benefit, not the firſt limited time of the expiration of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>were the Ground of the Bill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="33">33 <hi>W.W.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">33 And vacated by his own conſent.</note> was Summoned to appear before the King and his Counſel, and had Counſel learned, who ſtrongly oppoſed the vacating of his Patent, and the other Contents of His Majeſty's Order, till His Majeſty had put an end to the Hearing; ſo that Mr. <hi>Fitz G.</hi> urgeth directly contrary here to what he hath acknowledged in this his State of the Caſe. See <hi>pag. 7.</hi> and his own Knowledge, for he being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſaw that <hi>VV. W.</hi> did withſtand the vacating of his Patent by his Counſel, as long as they were ſuffered to ſtay till the Hearing was over, and that both <hi>W. VV.</hi> and his Counſel, and all that attended on his Account by Command, had withdrawn.</p>
               <p n="34">34 <note place="margin">34 As will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the hearing.</note> No ſuch thing did or could appear at the Hearing either before the Committee of the Houſe of Commons, or before the Committee of Lords, as all that were there can teſtifie.</p>
               <p>Let the World therefore judge whether theſe Inſinuations are not frivolous and unjuſt pretences.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Fitz-G.</hi> by the liberty he uſually takes in his Expreſſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>VV. VV.</hi> and by his Reflections upon him, labours to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Mens minds from the deſire of employing him, and would make them believe that he deſerves not to have any Encouragement given him; but it is well known <hi>W. VV.</hi> hath been often put to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt proofs of his Temper, of the truth of his VVords, and the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of his Experiments, yet therein was never found to come oft with Diſhonour, wherefore he hopes, he hath given no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for others upon any of theſe perſons Allegations, or on whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver account elſe, to diſtruſt his Credit, or ſincerity in any thing.</p>
               <p>NOW if notwithſtanding all the Cares, Toyls, Charges, and Difficulties <hi>W. W.</hi> hath himſelf laboured through, whereby he hath accompliſhed ſo Excellent an Art for the Publick USE; and notwithſtanding the Invicible Evidence given of the ſufficiency of his Art; and ſuch Teſtimony at home and abroad declaring it: <hi>W. W.</hi> cannot be received and reſtored to his Right; but ſtill meet with powerfull oppoſition, and ſtill lie under mighty diſcountenance to diſcourage, and force him to give off his hopes of proceeding; his Spirits and Strength will at length fail, that he muſt retire and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Fate, and then the Art will be loſt: Together with the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97399:14"/>Knowledge and Experience he hath gained by many Experiments and curious Diſquiſitions in ſeveral kinds, chiefly for the compleating of this Art; which if well digeſted into a methodical Diſcourſe, and made known, might alſo be highly uſeful to the Publick in many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent reſpects: But if none do regard the benefit, theſe may bring, it is not for him further to put himſelf after ſo much loſs ſuſtained, to the Labour and Coſt to expoſe his Notions to the publick Cenſure.</p>
               <p>William Walcot <hi>Humbly deſires that thoſe Honourable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both Houſes of Parliament, that have ſpent ſo much Time, and taken ſuch care to Examine the matter, and to paſs his Bill, will not at length ſuffer all to be loſt; that the Honourable the Houſe of Commons, that ſo unanimouſly Voted for the Bill, and recommended it to the Lords for their Concurrence, will give it new Encouragement. And that the Right Honourable the Houſe of Lords; the Committee of the Lords having in the ſame Seſſion</hi> 1692. <hi>Paſſed his Bill, will take it again into their Conſideration, That they may give their Conſent, eſpecially ſince it is manifeſt, it may be for the Publick Benefit of the Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>To ſpeak of the mighty Advantages <hi>W. W.</hi> his Art might yield at Sea, and Land requires a Treatiſe by it ſelf.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97399:14"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
